<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study>
  <required_header>
    <download_date>Information obtained from ClinicalTrials.gov on March 10, 2010</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00576927</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01 AG028769</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01 AG028769</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00576927</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving Sleep in Nursing Homes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Improving Sleep in Nursing Homes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Older people living in nursing homes do not sleep very well for many reasons. Sleep
      disorders such as sleep apnea (when someone briefly stops breathing during sleep), and night
      time urination, along with the problems caused by the nighttime environment of the nursing
      home, such as noise and disruptive care routines can all contribute.  Poor sleep can lead to
      other health problems or make existing health problems worse.

      This study will evaluate how well a sleep hygiene intervention and a medication for sleep
      (ramelteon (Rozerem)) work to improve sleep in nursing home residents with poor sleep.
      Ramelteon is FDA approved and has been tested in older adults living in the community, but
      not in older adults living in nursing homes.  We expect sleep to improve on the study drug
      along with the sleep hygiene intervention, in comparison to placebo along with the sleep
      hygiene intervention. Based on adverse events reported in previous samples of older
      subjects, we expect the study drug to cause few side effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates how well Ramelteon works by measuring sleep at night and during the
      day. After consenting and final determination of eligibility, participants will complete a
      baseline phase to assess usual sleep, as well as daytime alertness and activity , thinking
      and memory, walking and balance (among those who walk and/or stand), and mood. Sleep at
      night and during the day will be objectively assessed with wrist actigraphs in all subjects.
       Approximately half will also receive polysomnography to assess nighttime sleep.  Subjects
      who sleep more than 75% of the time they are in bed will not continue in the study.
      Subjects that do not have improved sleep with the sleep hygiene program will be randomized
      to one of two treatment groups - one will receive the active drug along with the sleep
      hygiene intervention and the other will receive a placebo along with the sleep hygiene
      intervention.  Following randomization, subjects will complete a brief run-in phase and then
      enter the treatment phase. Assessment of sleep and other measures will be repeated.

      The primary hypotheses to be examined in this study are as follows:

      Hypothesis 1: Subjects treated with ramelteon in addition to a sleep hygiene (SHI)  will
      have improved sleep latency, and as a consequence, a significant increase in actigraphically
      measured sleep efficiency, compared to subjects treated with placebo plus a SHI.

      Hypothesis 2: Subjects treated with ramelteon in addition to a SHI will sleep less and spend
      less time in bed during the day, be more engaged in daytime activities, and have better mood
      than subjects treated with placebo plus a SHI.

      Hypothesis 3: Changes in daytime sleep, time in bed during the day, engagement in
      activities, and mood will be positively correlated with improved sleep efficiency among
      subjects receiving ramelteon in addition to a SHI.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2007</start_date>
  <end_date>August 2009</end_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2009</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Treatment, Randomized, Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Placebo Control, Parallel Assignment, Efficacy Study</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep efficiency - Actigraphy measures- average percentage of time in bed at night asleep holding constant time in bed and recording time.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 nights of measures during 3 study phases</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other objective sleep parameters - as assessed by observations, daytime sleep, activity and behavior, PSG studies, Actigraphy  Mood</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 3 of 5 nights of data</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">835</enrollment>
  <condition>Sleep Deprivation</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ramelteon</intervention_name>
  <description>Subjects demonstrating low sleep efficiencies and prolonged sleep latencies,  will be randomly assigned to continue to receive SHI accompanied by either placebo or Ramelteon (8 mg). Matching placebo will be obtained and the medication pre-packaged and ordered based on the randomization results.</description>
  <other_name>Rozerem</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  After initial screening and consenting, subjects with a 5-night average baseline
             sleep efficiency of less than or equal to 75% will be included

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Less than 65 yrs old

          -  Bedbound

          -  Resided in NH for less than two months

          -  Patients on Medicare Part A skilled Benefit(anticipated short length stay)    -
             Terminal Illness

          -  Unstable psychotropic drug regimen  (addition, discontinuation,   or change of dosage
             of any psychotropic drug in the prior two weeks)     - Use of hypnotic,
             antihistamine, or benzodiazepine more than once per  week during the two weeks before
             screening

          -  Use of drugs that could potentially inhibit the metabolism of Ramelteon  (ie:
             fluvoxamine, ketoconazole, fluconazole)

          -  Use of Drugs that induce the metabolism of Ramelteon (ie: rifampin)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph G Ouslander, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University, School of Medicine, Geriatric Division</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Deborah R Wittig-Wells, RN, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>404-728-6906</phone>
    <email>dwittig@emory.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>A. G. Rhodes Home</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30312</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <verification_date>December 2007</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 17, 2007</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 17, 2007</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
  <name_title>Dr. Joseph G. Ouslander, MD</name_title>
  <organization>Emory University, School of Medicine, Division of Geriatrics</organization>
  </responsible_party>
</clinical_study>